Finding Aid for the Getty Research Institute Scholars Program Images and Recordings, 1985-2013 IA20026
Institutional Records and Archives
Getty Research Institute Scholars Program images and recordings
1985-2013
Institutional Records and Archives
Getty Research Institute. Scholars and Seminars Program
Getty Center for the History of Art and the Humanities. Scholars and Conferences Department
Getty Center for the History of Art and the Humanities. Seminars and Scholars Program
Getty Research Institute. Scholars Program
Getty Research Institute. Department of Research and Education
IA20026
59 Linear Feet (67 boxes)
1741.37 GB (944 files)
The collection consists of digitized and analog audio recordings, video recordings, and photographs of the people and events related to the Scholars Program at the Getty Research Institute. The materials date 1985-2013 and include recordings and photographs of lectures, panel discussions, conferences, and other events hosted by the Getty Research Institute and given by Getty Scholars, staff, and invited speakers. The collection also includes portraits of the program scholars and photo releases signed by scholars.
Separated Materials
Restricted materials have been removed from this collection and returned to the department that created them.
Acquisition Information
The records in this finding aid originated from the following accessions: 1987.IA.26, 1994.IA.02, 1995.IA.02, 1996.IA.02, 1997.IA.01, 2006.IA.24, 2009.IA.41, and 2019.IA.31.
Technical Requirements
Use copies do not exist for all audio or video recordings in this collection. The production of use copies is required before access can be granted and may add a delay to research requests. Special handling and gloves are required for the handling of contact prints and negatives.
Access to digital files is available online through the links provided in the inventory. Due to rights restrictions, some online recordings are available to on-site researchers only.
Access Restrictions
The records described in accession 1987.IA.26, 1994.IA.02, 1995.IA.02, 1996.IA.02, 1997.IA.01, 2009.IA.41, and 2006.IA.24 are available for use by qualified researchers. Accession 2019.IA.31 is restricted to staff only.
Some materials are digitized and accessible online. Master recordings are restricted; use copies or online digital copies exist for most of the recordings. Absence of use copies is noted at the file level in this finding aid. Where use copies do not exist, production of use copies is required before access will be granted; this may delay research requests. Advanced notice is required. Some recordings are restricted to on-site use only or are not available at all at the request of the participants.
The following types of records are permanently closed: records containing personal information, records that compromise security or operations, legal communications, legal work product, and records related to donors. The J. Paul Getty Trust reserves the right to restrict access to any records held by the Institutional Archives.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection comprises audio recordings, video recordings, and photographs of the people and events related to the Getty Research Institute Scholars Program and its predecessors, dating from 1985 to 2013.
The audiovisual recordings primarily comprise audiocassette and compact disc recordings of lectures, panel discussions, conferences, and other events hosted by the Getty Research Institute and given by Getty Scholars, staff, and invited speakers, dating from 1987 to 2001. Many of the recordings have been digitized. The lectures and events hosted by the Scholars Program tend to focus on the given theme for that particular scholar year. Other symposia and conferences represented in this collection cover various topics, and, although held at a Getty facility and attended by Getty Scholars, may not have been hosted by the Scholars Program. Also included are video tapes of a symposium on Florentine patronage (1986-1987) and a viewing schedule covering the research theme of the Getty Scholars Program for the 1986/1987 year: "Seventeenth Century Dutch Art and Society/Patronage."
The images principally comprise portraits of scholars from 1985 to 2007, contact sheets, negatives, and oversize photograph prints (8"x10" and 11"x14"). The photographs were primarily used to select official scholar portraits, but they also document to a lesser extent the outings, events, and lectures that Getty Scholars attended.
The collection also includes restricted photo releases signed by scholars from 1997 to 2013.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged into four series. Please note that Series III and IV are available for staff use only.
Series I. Audio recordings, 1987-2001
Series II. Video recordings, 1986-1987
Series III. Photographs, 1985-2007 (restricted) and
Series IV. Photo Releases, 1997-2013 (restricted).
Administrative History
The Getty Research Institute (GRI) is a program developed and overseen by the J. Paul Getty Trust, an international cultural and philanthropic organization serving both general audiences and specialized professionals. The Trust is a not-for-profit institution, educational in purpose and character that focuses on the visual arts in all of their dimensions. The Trust currently supports and oversees four programs: the J. Paul Getty Museum; the Getty Foundation; the Getty Conservation Institute; and the Getty Research Institute (GRI).
Located at the Getty Center in the Brentwood neighborhood of Los Angeles, California, the GRI creates and disseminates new knowledge through its expertise, its active collecting program, public programs, institutional collaborations, exhibitions, publications, digital services, and residential scholars program. The GRI also provides intellectual leadership through its research projects and its innovative digital reference tools. The GRI's Research Library, consisting of over one million books, periodicals, study photographs, auction catalogs and special collections of rare and unique materials, serve an international community of scholars and the interested public. The activities and scholarly resources of the GRI guide and sustain each other and, together, provide a unique environment for research, critical inquiry, and debate. The origins of the J. Paul Getty Trust date to 1953, when J. Paul Getty established the J. Paul Getty Museum as a California charitable trust to house his growing art collections. Originally a small, private institution located in Mr. Getty's Ranch House near Malibu, California, the museum moved to the newly constructed Getty Villa on grounds adjacent to the Ranch House in 1974. When most of Mr. Getty's personal estate passed to the Trust in 1982, the Trustees decided that, given the size of the endowment, it should make a greater contribution to the visual arts and humanities than the museum could alone.
The establishment of an arts library had already been proposed as early as 1977 by then Museum Director Stephen Garrett, when in February 1982, Trust President Harold Williams' chief deputy Nancy Englander outlined a proposed "Center for Advanced Study." This proposed center would include a residence program for scholars, a major expansion of the library, a limited publications program, and an art photo archive. The center would focus on the preservation of historic art history materials and the development of new art history reference tools using state-of-the-art information technology. The plan was approved and the Getty Center for the History of the Arts and the Humanities (GCHAH) opened in temporary quarters in the First Federal Building at 401 Wilshire Boulevard, Santa Monica, in July 1983. In 1996, in order to avoid confusion with the soon-to-open Getty Center in Brentwood, the GCHAH was renamed the Getty Research Institute for the History of Art and the Humanities. In 2000, the program's name was shortened to the GRI.
Noted architectural historian Kurt Forster began work as the first director of the GCHAH in the fall of 1984. One of the original departments in the GCHAH was the Visiting Scholars and Conferences department, headed by Herb Hymans, and it was this department that inaugurated the Scholars Program in the fall of 1985, inviting 17 scholars and fellows to explore the theme "Aesthetic Experience and Affinities Among the Arts." Since that first year, the number of scholars has fluctuated between 20 and 30, but the treatment and consideration of a specific theme has remained a constant.
In addition to hosting the Scholars Program, the Visiting Scholars and Conferences department was also responsible for organizing scholarly activities, events, and conferences. The department went through several name changes and restructuring in the years that followed. In the mid-1990s, it was renamed the Scholars and Seminars Program and later renamed the Scholars and Conferences Department. In 1998, its activities were encompassed in the new Department of Research and Education, which included the development of new art historical scholarship and to consolidate programming activities. As a result of the GRI reorganization in 2009, the department was split into two: a new department, Research Projects and Programs, and the Scholars Program dedicated to scholar activities. As of 2009, the Scholars Program reports directly to the Director of the GRI.
Related Materials
The following materials are offered as possible sources of further information on the people and subjects covered by the records. The listing is not exhaustive.
Getty Institutional Archives
J. Paul Getty Museum Guest Scholar and Conservator Files, J. Paul Getty Museum. Institutional Archives, Research Library, Getty Research Institute. (IA10013).
Getty Villa Event Recordings, J. Paul Getty Museum. The Getty Research Institute (IA20035).
J. Paul Getty Museum Getty Center public event recordings, Getty Research Institute. The Getty Research Institute (IA20037).
Getty Research Institute Public Event recordings, Getty Research Institute. The Getty Research Institute (IA40002).
J. Paul Getty Museum Performing arts recordings and ephemera, J. Paul Getty Museum. The Getty Research Institute (IA40012).
Additional Information Available
Additional information regarding Getty Scholar years, themes, and participants can be accessed on the Getty site at: http://hdl.handle.net/10020/grischolarsprogram.
Please note that scholar event recordings created from Scholar Year 2001/2002 through the present are not listed in this inventory. Lists of recordings from 2001/2002 and following are part of broader collections and are available through the following inventories:
The Getty Research Institute Public Event Recordings (for events related to modern and contemporary topics that were held at the GRI)
The Getty Villa Event Recordings (for events related to ancient cultures and antiquities that were held at the Getty Villa).
Most of the public Getty Scholar recordings from 2001/2002 forward have also been described individually. For additional information on a particular event, search the Getty Research Institute Library Catalog by event name or participant name.
Learning and scholarship; Sound recordings; Congresses and conventions; Contact sheets; Video recordings; Negatives (Photographs); Videocassettes; Lectures; Art historians -- Research; Audiocassettes; Electronic records (digital records); Digital media
- Audio recordings, 1987-2001; Series I.; 21.7 Linear Feet (27 boxes); 1741.37 GB (944 files)
  Arrangement
  The recordings are arranged chronologically by academic year (September through June) into the following subseries:
  Series I.A. Scholar Year 1986-1987
  Series I.B. Scholar Year 1987-1988
  Series I.C. Scholar Year 1988-1989
  Series I.D. Scholar Year 1989-1990
  Series I.E. Scholar Year 1990-1991
  Series I.F. Scholar Year 1991-1992
  Series I.G. Scholar Year 1992-1993
  Series I.H. Scholar Year 1993-1994
  Series I.I. Scholar Year 1994-1995
  Series I.J. Scholar Year 1995-1996
  Series I.K. Scholar Year 1996-1997
  Series I.L. Scholar Year 1997-1998 and 1998-1999
  Series I.M. Scholar Year 1999-2000
  Series I.N. Scholar Year 2000-2001.
  Scope and Contents
  The material consists of audiocassette and compact disc recordings of lectures, panel discussions, conferences, and other events hosted by the Getty Research Institute (and its predecessors) and given by Getty Scholars, staff, and invited speakers, 1987-2001. Every year since 1985 the Research Institute has invited scholars, artists, and other cultural figures from around the world to work in residence at the Institute on projects that bear upon its annual research theme. While in residence, they pursue their own research projects, make use of Getty collections, and participate in the intellectual life of the Getty Center and the Getty Villa.The lectures and events hosted by the Scholars Program tend to focus on the given theme for that particular scholar year (see Past Themes and Scholars in Residence for a list of past scholars and scholar year themes). Other lectures and events represented in this collection, although held at the Getty Center and attended by Getty Scholars, were not specifically hosted by the Scholars Program and cover varied topics. These include ongoing series such as Works-in-Progress as well as special symposia and conferences held at the Getty Center.
  Additional Information Available
  Please note that scholar event recordings created from Scholar Year 2001/2002 through the present are not listed in this inventory. Lists of recordings from 2001/2002 and following are part of broader collections and are available through the following inventories:
  The Getty Research Institute Public Event Recordings (for events related to modern and contemporary topics that were held at the GRI)
  The Getty Villa Event Recordings (for events related to ancient cultures and antiquities that were held at the Getty Villa).
  Most of the public Getty Scholar recordings from 2001/2002 forward have also been described individually. For additional information on a particular event, search the Getty Research Institute Library Catalog by event name or participant name.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Access to digital files is available online through the links provided in the inventory. Due to rights restrictions, some online recordings are available to on-site researchers only.
  The quality of the recordings varies. Audience members are often difficult to hear during discussions / question and answer sessions. Incomplete recordings are noted when known.
  Access Restrictions
  Institutional Archives is in the process of creating access copies of the audio recordings. Online versions of the audio recordings have been created for scholar year 1986/1987 through 2000/2001. Online versions of the recordings are available to on-site researchers only. A researcher may request access of recordings available for on-site access only by placing a request through the Getty's Interlibrary Loan program.
  - Scholar Year 1986-1987, Series I.A.; 52.43 GB (36 files)
    The recordings are grouped first by symposia/theme, followed by a group of more general lectures and presentations. Within each group, the recordings are in chronological order.
    Materials comprise recordings of events, lectures, and discussions held at the Getty during the scholar year 1986/1987. During this time Getty Scholars explored two research themes: Seventeenth Century Dutch painting and the broader issues of art patronage. The scholars were drawn from disciplines ranging from art history to economic history. While most of the lectures given during this academic year were inspired by the scholar theme "Seventeenth Century Dutch Art and Society/Patronage," some of the lectures are not thematically related.
    Due to rights restrictions, online versions of the recordings are available to on-site researchers only. A researcher may request use copies (CDs) of specific recordings for in-library use at a local library by placing a request through the Getty's Interlibrary Loan program.
    - Conference on the Interrelationship of Art History and History of 17th Century Holland, April 30-May 2, 1987; Series I.A.1.; (13 audiocassettes and 1 set of copies)
      Materials comprise audio recordings of lectures, panel discussions, conferences, and other events hosted by the Getty Research Institute and given by Getty Scholars, staff, and invited speakers. The lectures and events hosted by the Scholar Program tend to focus on the given theme for that particular academic year. These recordings are from a conference held in the academic year 1986/1987, during which Getty Scholars explored two research themes: Seventeenth Century Dutch painting and the broader issues of art patronage. The scholars were drawn from disciplines ranging from art history to economic history.
      - Session 1, April 30, 1987
        - Hymans, Herb. Opening remarks, 0002a1 (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - Smit, J. "History in Art", 0002a2 (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - Schwartz, Gary. "Art in History", 0002b (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - De Jongh, E. "Limitations of Interpretation", 0004a (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - Panel Discussion: Session 1, 0004b (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
      - Session 2: [Art and Reality], May 1, 1987
        - De Vries, Jan. Introduction, 0006a1 (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - Brandenburg, W. A. "Market Scenes as Seen by a Plant Biologist", 0006a2 (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - Stone-Ferrier, Linda. "Market Scenes as Seen by an Art Historian", 0006b (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - Panel Discussion: Art and Reality, part 1, 0008a (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - Falkenberg, Reindert. "Market Scenes and Kitchen Pieces", 0008b (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - Becker, Jochen. "Kitchen Scenes", 0010a1 (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - Panel Discussion: Art and Reality, part 2, 0010a2 (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - Unger, Richard. "Dutch and Flemish Marine Paintings as a Source for Research on the History of Shipbuilding", 0010b (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - Walsh, John. "Skies and Reality", 0012a (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - Panel Discussion: Art and Reality, part 3, 0012b (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
      - Session 3: [Art, Economy, and Society], May 1, 1987
        - De Vries, Jan. "Can Economic History Provide a Sound Base for Defining Periods Useful to Art History?", 0014a (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - Van der Wowde, A. "A First Estimation of the Quantitative Dimensions of Dutch Art Production During the Golden Age", 0014b (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - Montias, J. Michael. "What Can We Learn About 'Art, Economy and Society' from Analysis of 17th century Inventories of Works of Art?", 0016a (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - Panel Discussion: Art, Economy, and Society, 0016b (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
      - Session 4: [The Town Hall of Amsterdam], May 2, 1987
        - Schwartz, Gary. Introduction, 0018a1 (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - Van Heel, C. Dudok. [The Burgermeisters of Amsterdam], 0018a2 (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - Blankert, Albert. [Painted Decoration of the Town Hall and Other Public Buildings of Amsterdam], 0018b (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - Spies, Marijke. [A Poem's Commentary: Poems on the Walls of the Town Hall?], 0020a (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
          The speaker is introduced by Gary Schwartz.
        - Schama, Simon. [Grand Eloquence and Austerity: Dutch Civic Architecture?], 0020b1 (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - Panel Dicussion: [The Town Hall of Amsterdam], 0020b2 (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
      - Session 5, May 2, 1987
        - J. Smit. Introduction, 0022a1 (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - Judson, J.R. "History and Changes in Style", 0022a2 (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - De Vries, Lyckle, "Can Stylistic Art History Provide a Viable Way to Define Periods Within the Art History of the Netherlands", 0022b (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - Hauerkamp-Begemann, Egbert. "The Role of Connoisseurship in Art History.", 0024a (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - Freedberg, David. "Art in History: Some Further Possibilities", 0024b (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - Closing Discussions, May 2, 1987; 0026 (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
    - Lectures and presentations, Series I.A.2.; (7 audiocassettes)
      - Boulez, Pierre. Lecture at the Getty Center, March 16, 1987; 0001; (1 audiocassette) (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
      - Corboz, André lecture, May 26, 1987; (2 audiocassettes)
        - [Transformation of Solomon's Temple] Part 1, 0028 (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
        - [Transformation of Solomon's Temple] Part 2, 0029 (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
      - Hollander, Anne. [Evolution of Masculine Costume], June 10, 1987; 0030; (2 audiocassettes) (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
      - Schwartz, Gary. [The Painter Nearly Poet: Rembrandt and Dutch Literary Life], June 17, 1987; 0032; (2 audiocassettes) (Box 1996.IA.02-1)
  - Scholar Year 1987-1988, Series I.B.; 35.24 GB (12 files); (12 audiocassettes)
    Materials comprise recordings of events, lectures, and discussions held at the Getty during the scholar year 1987/1988. During this time Getty Scholars pursued individual areas of research while also exploring the theme of reception and interpretation of works of art and cultural products. Scholars approached this theme from their personal areas of expertise, which ranged from photography through ethnomathematics. While many of the lectures given during this academic year were inspired by the scholar theme: "Reception and Interpretation of the Arts," some of the recordings are not thematically related.
    The recordings are listed in chronological order.
    A researcher may request access of recordings available for on-site access only by placing a request through the Getty's Interlibrary Loan program.
    - Lüthy, Hans. [Escapism], October 20, 1987; 0034; (1 audiocassette) (Box 1996.IA.02-2)
    - Burckhardt, Jacqueline. "Parkett Art Magazine" Lecture and Discussion, October 28, 1987; 0035; (1 audiocassette) (Box 1996.IA.02-2)
      General
      Audio quality of roundtable discussion is choppy, inconsistent, and ends mid-sentence.
    - Lowry, Martin. [Warwick in the Age of the Kingmaker: The Impact of Patronage on the Small Town], November 24, 1987; 0036; (1 audiocassette) (Box 1996.IA.02-2)
    - Shefton, Brian. [Grand Tour Collecting in 18th Century Britain], December 8, 1987; 0037; (1 audiocassette) (Box 1996.IA.02-2)
    - Brandt-Sorensen Presentation, February 23, 1988; 0038; (1 audiocassette) (Box 1996.IA.02-2)
    - Pare, Richard. [Late-Ninteenth-Century Documentary Photography of Architecture and How it Overlaps with Fine Art Photography], March 1, 1988; 0039; (1 audiocassette) (Box 1996.IA.02-2)
    - Hoye, Daniel. [The Residential Architecture of Los Angeles as a Backdrop for the History of the City], March 11, 1988; 0040; (1 audiocassette) (Box 1996.IA.02-2)
    - Breisch, Ken. "The Metamorphosis of the Wall: Reflections of Ruskin and Nineteenth-Century architectural theory in the Historical Photographs of John Henry Parker,", March 15, 1988; 0041; (1 audiocassette) (Box 1996.IA.02-2)
    - Shiff, Richard. "Artist, Critic, and Historian: To Be or Merely to Appear,", May 11, 1988; 0042; (1 audiocassette) (Box 1996.IA.02-2)
    - Freund, Gisèle. [Photography and her work as a photojournalist], May 16, 1988; 0043; (1 audiocassette) (Box 1996.IA.02-2)
    - Warner, Marina. "From the Beast to the Blonde: Peau d'Âne (Donkeyskin),", May 24, 1988; 0044; (1 audiocassette) (Box 1996.IA.02-2)
    - Nodelman, Sheldon. [Marcel Duchamp, Encore á cet Astre (Once More to This Star)], June 7, 1988; 0045; (1 audiocassette) (Box 1996.IA.02-2)
  - Scholar Year 1988-1989, Series I.C.; 66.09 GB (29 files)